Hello and welcome to our lecture on solid state
computing. We've got a lot to cover. At the end
of the previous lecture, we were talking about
the Colossus and how the tube was replacing the
relay in in digital applications. And now we're
going to talk about the transistor, its invention,
and how eventually it replaces tubes in digital
applications because the transistor is faster,
less heat, reliable, so many things. We're going
to talk about amplifiers, tubes, and transistors,
but it's complicated. Transistor radios are were
made possible by transistors, but audio files
uh still like their tubes. We'll talk about that
in a bit. We're going to talk about how over time
we got better and better at manufacturing uh
transistors. And their underlying transistor
technology has changed over time. And so the way
we think about this is we create this concept
of a digital logic gate which is an abstraction
which is the same and the underlying transistor
technology for a digital logic gate can be very
different but the way we think about digital logic
gates is the way we can it's irrespective of the
underlying technology or manufacturing technology
and then transistors increased in density and
scale and eventually we will learn about very
largecale integration VLSI and learn how we lay
out chips and how to manufacture them and just
play with that just a little bit. But let's start
at the beginning with vacuum tubes. Right? So the
Colossus we used valves. The more British way to
call it is valves. And I think that to some degree
valves is a good way to think about it because
it is sort of a a remote control valve that sort
of allows less or more electricity through a
particular thing based on an input value. And
its initial design was to design analog amplify
signals things like long-distance phone calls. You
know, you have a microphone and a thousand miles
away there's a speaker or a 100 miles away there's
a speaker. And so the problem is is the amount of
voltage that a microphone would generate is just
not enough to get through hundreds of miles of
wires. So about every 10 miles you needed a power
supply and an amplifier where the wires would
come off down off of the poles, get amplified,
be put back up on the poles. And the tube is a
relatively old concept. It was invented in 1912
by Dr. Lee Deforest. So let me show you closeup
a couple things about tubes and relays because
the Colossus really was the transition from tubes
to relays. This is a relay. And in this device,
there's a series of inputs, inputs and
outputs. And there's a bunch of switches,
but then there's a control input and output. And
the control input and output is what I'm going to
be playing with. Control input output. So, I'm
going to be putting electricity on the control
input. And what you've got is a spring that keeps
contacts one way and then an an electromagnet that
pulls the contacts another way. So, I've got a
little tiny power DC power supply. It's a simple
little DC power supply. It's pretty safe. Um, and
I'm going to activate this. And so, right now,
the contacts right there, the contacts
are one way. And when I activate this,
the contacts click to the other way. And you
can kind of see the contacts moving back and
forth. And you can think of that as a zero and a
one. And on things like the Bomba, we use these
kinds of relays to capture zeros and ones. And you
can even use these eventually to do addition. The
problem with relays and why tubes are better
is how fast can you move this back and forth,
right? It's like I'm a video gamer pushing the
keys as fast as I can. The problem is is because
there is inertia, there's a spring, and there's
physics. There's only a certain amount of speed
that you can get to it. And so ultimately tubes
don't make a clicking noise. Anything that's
physical digital makes a clicking noise. So I'm
going to I'm going to connect this and keep this
connected and show you one more thing. So So now
this is energized and I'll turn it I'll turn my
voltage down to zero. So now it's a zero. Now it's
a one. Now it's a zero. But I don't know if you're
hearing it. I'll try to make it so you can hear it
even better. There's a moment where this device,
the physics is confused. The the amount of
voltage going through the electromagnet is
not strong enough to override the little spring
at the top. There's a spring right there. And
so you see that it's fighting. Okay. So the the
electromagnet and the spring are fighting. And let
me make the electromagnet and the spring fight.
And what you'll see at the bottom here is you'll
see this kind of bouncing back and forth. And
from a from a digital perspective, it's bouncing
back and forth from zero to one. So here I'm
going to start it. And as I move it up slowly,
you may not be able to see the movement, but you
probably can hear the movement. It is just biting
and the and it and it's going back and forth
and and it's neither zero nor one at this point.
If I go up higher then it will then it will then
it switches and it stops. And that transition is
an important part of turning analog devices into
digital devices because we have to compensate for
that. We have to make sure that whatever voltage
it is that leaves this in an intermediate state
halfway between zero and one is something we
compensate for with logic outside of this device.
So here I have some consumer packaging. And in
the 1950s and the 1960s, we would have radios
and televisions in our homes, and we would have
to go to the store and buy new tubes when the
tubes broke down. So this tube that I showed
you before actually has a number. Its number is
uh 6 CG8A. And after this, I will show you the
spec that you can still read online for that. The
other thing that's interesting is the packaging.
It's a little paper, but it was designed for you
to go to the store and to be able to bring home
this somewhat fragile device and not break it. So,
here is the tube I showed you before,
and we'll look at the specification,
and you'll see the the pins. There's nine pins. It
talks about the height, and you'll see a bunch of
graphs as compared to if you put certain amounts
of electricity and voltage on certain pins, then
certain things happen. And so, there's a whole
bunch of graphs. So later I'll start telling you
talking to you about those graphs in the abstract.
Here are the specifications of the 6 CG8A. It says
nine. It has nine inputs. It's about two and 2.1
in tall. And you can see which inputs go to the
grid, which inputs go to the heater and which
inputs are go to the output voltage that then
is the amplified output voltage. We have these
physical devices, these digital tubes, and their
original purpose was to do amplification. And to
do amplification, well, you want a nice smooth
transition as your input voltage is increased. You
want a smooth transition for your output voltage.
You want the output voltage to be higher, but you
also want it to be smooth because you're trying
to do an amplification. And so the right curve
has a nice sort of 45deree angle linear sloped
amplification. The problem is is that the when
when you have such a long time before it kind
of goes from the low voltage to the high voltage
that makes the transition period too long. So the
there's a voltage range that's a zero, there's a
voltage range that's transition and then there's
a voltage range that is one. So by changing
the sizes of things and resistance etc you can
build a a a valve that is not as good of an audio
amplifier but more suitable for digital. And what
you want to do is you want to take the transition
period from sort of 0 to one and make that more
narrow meaning that it goes quickly from quiet to
loud in a sense more quickly than you'd want for
a real amplifier. And you kind of want it at the
1/3 point, right? So you as the input voltage goes
from zero to the 1/3 point, it's kind of zero.
And then there's a short transition, but by the
time it gets to like half of the input voltage,
the output is a one. So you know, you could the
the input could be from zero.1.2.3.4.5, 4.5. But
by the time the input voltage is halfway to one,
the output volt voltage is one. And this allows
for what we call regeneration. So if a circuit has
an output that we want to be a zero or one, and
we want that to be an input to another circuit,
then we can regenerate that. So you might get like
0.7 coming from a previous circuit and then want
it to be one going into the next circuit. And
so the idea is you tune these things so they
go up quickly and to some degree early so that
we get through a fast transition stage and a a
long regeneration stage so that you always can
can predictably have a zero or a one even with
a very analog device. So valves as we've talked
they take a lot of power they generate a lot of
heat. Most of the tubes have heaters inside them
that made it easier for the the electrons to come
off the cathode. They're physically large. You
you know how many how many gigabytes can you put?
You can't. You know, a 100 bytes would be large
to to build with tubes. They're expensive and
complex to manufacture because they're made of
glass. They have tiny little wires in them that
are hard to manufacture and put together. And
they have to be a vacuum. They do have a soft
electronic glow-in-the-dark. The soft electronic
glow-in-the-dark is to some an advantage. And of
course, from a technology and electronics
perspective, when we think about computers,
they're a disadvantage. So, up next, we're
going to talk about the semiconductors,
which begin to address some of the disadvantages
of valves/vacuum tubes. [Music] [Applause] [Music]